<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Stockbridge-Munsee Council Bylaws for Police and Fire Commission" name="2024">
  <heading>POLICE AND FIRE COMMISSION BYLAWS</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>I</num>
    <heading>Authority</heading>
    <section>
      <num>1.1</num>
      <text>Name. The name of this entity shall be the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission and may be referred to as the Police and Fire Commission.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.2</num>
      <text>Authority. This entity was established under the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Resolution #013-12 on December 20, 2011.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.3</num>
      <text>Office. The official mailing address of this entity shall be:</text>
      <text>Stockbridge-Munsee Police Department</text>
      <text>W13455 Camp 14 Road</text>
      <text>Bowler, WI 54416</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.4</num>
      <text>Membership. The Police and Fire Commission will be made up of five (5) Stockbridge-Munsee Community Members:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text><em>How Appointed</em>. All members of the Police and Fire Commission shall be appointed by the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council. The initial appointment of Commission members shall be for 1-year, 2-years, 3-years, 4-years and 5-years with such terms designated by lot. Thereafter, all appointments to the Police and Fire Commission shall be for five (5) year staggered terms.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text><em>How Vacancies are filled</em>. Vacancies on the Police and Fire Commission shall be filled by appointment by the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council for the duration of the unexpired term.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text><em>Qualifications</em>. All Police and Fire Commission members:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Must be a enrolled member of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribe;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Must be 25 years of age or older;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Must cooperate with the completion of a complete background investigation by the Stockbridge-Munsee Community's Compliance Department. The Compliance Department will forward their findings to the Tribal Council for consideration as part of the appointment process. Applicants who have one of the following issues are prohibited from serving on the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>A felony conviction in the State of Wisconsin or any conviction of a crime in another state that would be considered a felony conviction if the offense and adjudication occurred in the State of Wisconsin.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>A felony arrest which results in a misdemeanor conviction due to a plea arrangement.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Must submit to drug testing prior to appointment and on an annual basis;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Must not be an employee of the Stockbridge-Munsee Police Department, Stockbridge-Munsee Volunteer Fire Department or any employee the Police Chief or Fire Chief supervises, Tribal Court, Legal Department, or Tribal Council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Shall attend applicable training;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Must be a person of known good standing in the community.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text><em>Removal from Office.</em> A Police and Fire Commission member may be removed by the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council for:</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Malfeasance in office; Conduct which could jeopardize the reputation of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribe, the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission or the law enforcement system; Any change in status which would place the Commission member in conflict with the qualifications specified in section 1.4 (c); Proven violation of the confidentiality of a closed hearing or any other information declared "confidential" by the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission; Serious neglect of duty as a Commission member, including but not limited to failure to appear at three (3) consecutive meetings without a valid reason of which all such charges shall be documented by the Police and Fire Commission in the minutes.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.5</num>
      <text>Resignation. Resignations from the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission shall be in writing and presented to the Tribal Council.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>II</num>
    <heading>Officers</heading>
    <section>
      <num>2.1</num>
      <text>Officers. This entity shall have three (3) officers—Chair, Vice-Chair, and Secretary.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2.2</num>
      <text>Chair Duties. Responsible for calling meetings and notifying members with the assistance of the Secretary. The Chair shall preside over all regular and special meetings, shall sign all official Police and Fire Commission documents, shall be the liaison to the Tribal Council and other departments' heads and shall perform other duties consistent with the bylaws as determined by the Police and Fire Commission. The Chair shall seek clearance from the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council for any media requests made of the Police and Fire Commission. The Chair shall also ensure that the Police and Fire Commission remain fiscally responsible for any budget provided.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2.3</num>
      <text>Vice-Chair Duties. The Vice-Chair shall preside at all meetings in the absence of the Chair and appoint a Vice-Chair for that meeting. The Vice-Chair shall work with the Chair in all matters that concern the Police and Fire Commission. In the event of the resignation, removal from office or death of the Chair, the Vice-Chair shall assume the role of Chair until such time as the term of the Chair would have expired.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2.4</num>
      <text>Secretary Duties. The Secretary shall keep accurate minutes of all meetings, both regular and special, assuring that the minutes are reported in the proper format. The Secretary shall read and answer all mail abiding by/to the decision of the Police and Fire Commission.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2.5</num>
      <text>Selection Process and Term. The officers shall serve terms of one (1) year and shall be elected by a majority vote of the Police and Fire Commission. Terms of office run from the beginning of the fiscal year. In the event of a vacancy, the successor shall be elected by a majority vote of the Police and Fire Commission for the duration of the unexpired term.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>III</num>
    <heading>Meetings</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.1</num>
      <text>Regular Meetings. The designated meeting place for meetings shall be the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Public Safety Building.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The regular meeting of the Police and Fire Commission shall be held on a quarterly basis. Special meetings will be held as needed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Notice of meeting location, agenda and materials shall be forwarded by the Chair with the assistance of the Secretary.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.2</num>
      <text>Emergency &amp; Special Meetings. Special meetings may be called by the Chair or any three (3) members with at least a one (1) day notice.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.3</num>
      <text>Quorum. A quorum shall consist of three (3) members who shall include the Chair or the Vice-Chair.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.4</num>
      <text>Order of Business. The regular meetings of the Police and Fire Commission shall follow the order of business as set out herein:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Call to order,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Approval of the Agenda,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Reading of Minutes,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Correction and Approval of Minutes,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Correspondence and Mail,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Standing and Special Committee Reports,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Old Business,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>New Business,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Other,</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>Adjournment.</text>
      </para>
      <text>In order to facilitate the Police and Fire Commission's proceedings, the order of business may be amended or suspended at any time by a majority of the Commission members.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.5</num>
      <text>Closed Session. During any meeting, with proper notice, a closed session may be called for by any single member of the Police and Fire Commission for the purpose of discussing matters of a confidential nature. Closed Sessions are limited to Commission members and such invited persons as the Police and Fire Commission deems necessary. The meeting must be returned to "open session" following the "closed session."</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>IV</num>
    <heading>Stipend</heading>
    <section>
      <num>4.1</num>
      <text>All Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission members shall receive a stipend to be determined by the Tribal Council.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>V</num>
    <heading>Reporting</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.1</num>
      <text>Format. Agenda items shall be in an identified format.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.2</num>
      <text>Minutes. Minutes shall be typed or written and in a consistent format designed to generate the most informative record of the meetings of the Police and Fire Commission. Minutes shall be submitted to the Tribal Council for acceptance and shall be required before stipends are expended to Commission members.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.3</num>
      <text>Attachments. Handouts, reports, memoranda and the like may be attached to the minutes and agenda, or may be kept separately, provided that all materials can be identified to the meeting in which they are presented.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.4</num>
      <text>Reporting. The Police and Fire Commission will report the minutes to the Tribal Council. Reporting of the minutes shall be made within a reasonable time after a meeting is held and presented to the Tribal Council at a regular meeting in person by a member of the Police and Fire Commission, or as the Tribal Council and the Police and Fire Commission agree.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>VI</num>
    <heading>Role and Responsibilities</heading>
    <section>
      <num>6.1</num>
      <text>Role. The Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission shall function purely as an advisory and appellate body consistent with its responsibilities as identified in these Bylaws and shall have no control over the operational functions of the Stockbridge-Munsee Police and Volunteer Fire Departments.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>6.2</num>
      <text>Responsibilities. The Stockbridge-Munsee Community Police and Fire Commission shall:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Hear all allegations of officer misconduct in fulfilling his or her duties levied against the Police Chief of the Stockbridge-Munsee Police Department. The Commission shall make written findings based on their hearing and forward such findings and their recommendation to the designated administrative supervisor of the Police Chief. Such recommendations may include no action, a corrective action, suspending or removing the Police Chief. All allegations of personnel violations shall not be heard by the Police and Fire Commission but shall be handled in accordance with the normal employee grievance process. The Police Chief's designated administrative supervisor shall work with the Human Resources Department and Legal Department to determine whether an issue relates to conduct of an officer or is a personnel violation. When in doubt, the matter shall be heard by the Police and Fire Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Hear appeals of disciplinary actions taken by the Police Chief against any law enforcement personnel or non-sworn personnel that relate to allegations of officer misconduct in fulfilling his or her duties. Appeals related to personnel violations will be addressed in accordance with the normal employee grievance process. The Police Chief shall work with the Human Resources Department and Legal Department to determine whether an issue relates to conduct of an officer or is a personnel violation. When in doubt, the matter shall be heard by the Police and Fire Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Hear all allegations of officer misconduct in fulfilling his or her duties levied against the Fire Chief of the Stockbridge-Munsee Volunteer Fire Department. The Commission shall make written findings based on their hearing and forward such findings and their recommendation to the Tribal Council. As the Fire Chief is not an employee, he or she is not eligible for the employee grievance process.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Work with the Police Chief and the Fire Chief to develop and recommend to the Tribal Council law enforcement and fire department rules, regulations and policies that shall not violate the provisions of the Tribal Constitution, this ordinance, or any other Tribal Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Follow all applicable Tribal law including Chapter 51, Code of Conduct.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Avoid all conflicts of interest including perceived conflicts of interest and maintain the strictest confidentiality of all matters discussed before the Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Article</prefix>
    <num>VII</num>
    <heading>Amendments</heading>
    <section>
      <num>7.1</num>
      <text>Amendments to the By-Laws. Amendments to these by-laws shall be recommended to the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council at a regular meeting</text>
    </section>
  </container>
</document>
